2018年年底 第一艘Starship原型机开始逐渐成形
At the end of 2018, the first Starship prototype began to take shape.
在包下了一块德州的烂泥地之后
After taking over a dirt field in Texas,
太空叉踏上了他们送人类去火星的漫漫长路
SpaceX started a long journey of development with the hopes of taking humans to Mars.
两年后 Starship的进度也让无数人关注
Two years later and the progress of Starship has been mesmerizing.
从各种角度来说 Starship都是人类航天史上最具野心的火箭
In almost every way, Starship is more ambitious than any other rocket in the history of spaceflight.
究其原因 不但有安装的最先进的火箭发动机之一
Not only is it powered by one of the most advanced rocket engines ever made,
还有为了全部可回收而增加的复杂度
it also has the added complexities that are needed to be the first fully reusable rocket.
Starship无论设计还是建造都是一项挑战
Starship has been an incredible challenge to design and build,
但根据马一龙所说
but according to Elon Musk,
找到如何制造生产火箭的方法比想象中难得多
figuring out how to actually manufacture the rocket has been way more difficult.
尽管如此 太空叉的研发速度看起来也还挺快
Despite these challenges, SpaceX seems to be progressing at an absurd rate.
但太空叉需要解决的最困难的问题可能不在火箭本身
But one of the most challenging problems that SpaceX will need to solve isn't actually the rocket itself,
而是发射架
but the launch pad.
2020年11月9日 太空叉对其其中一艘Starship原型机执行了静态点火测试
On the 9th of November 2020, SpaceX performed a static fire with one of their Starship prototypes.
这是首次一艘完全组装的Starship产生推力
This was the first time a fully assembled Starship had produced thrust.
本次测试由一台发动机完成
The test was completed using a single engine
目的是验证头部的储箱可以在着陆时为发动机提供燃料
and was carried out to make sure the header tanks could feed fuel to the engine during a landing.
但测试并未按预计进行
But the test didn't exactly go to plan.
发动机点火后不久
Shortly after the engine fired up,
发射架下大量水泥块都被冲飞了
chunks of concrete were sent flying upwards from the base of the launch pad.
看着挺壮观 但对火箭的伤害也不小
Although it looked spectacular, it turned out to be a lot more damaging than it first seemed.
Martyte: a ceramic filled epoxy 填充陶瓷的环氧树脂[1]
火箭下的水泥平台有一层称为Martyte的涂层
The concrete pad beneath the rocket had an ablative coating called Martyte,
用于在点火测试的时候保护水泥平台
which was designed to protect the concrete during each test fire.
测试之后Martyte的任务就算完成了
Up until this point, the Martyte had done its job.
但经过几个月的测试
But after months of testing,
它终于被岁月磨平了棱角 露出了原本的水泥地 还被冲上了天
it had finally worn away and the exposed concrete was ripped up and thrown into the air.
一块水泥飞进了发动机舱
A chunk of concrete flew into the engine bay
破坏了一条电缆 最终导致一台发动机损毁
and severed an electrical cable which ended up damaging one of the engines.
尽管他们看到了这不寻常的水泥块起飞的现象
Despite this unusual sight of flying concrete,
太空叉还是决定在第二天再来一次静态点火试验
SpaceX came back the next day and decided to perform another static fire,
这次改用两台猛禽发动机
this time using two of their raptor engines.
测试中 发动机再一次把水泥块冲上了天
During the test, the engines once again sent concrete flying into the air -
但当发动机关机后 一个更大的问题显现出来
but once the engines shut down, a much bigger problem was observed.
火箭底部能明显看到一坨坨红热的液体淌到了发射台上
At the bottom of the vehicle, a glowing liquid was seen pouring out onto the launch pad.
最后发现 是猛禽发动机的内部结构被完全融化了
As it turned out, the internal components of the raptor engine had completely melted
那些红热的液体是融化的金属
and the glowing liquid was in fact molten metal.
这类损伤发生的原因是火箭底部没有导流槽
The reason this kind of damage was able to happen
is because there was no flame diverter underneath the rocket.
于是发动机的尾焰会垂直喷向水泥地
Instead, the force of the engines was hitting the concrete at a 90 degree angle,
在一点产生大量的热量
creating an enormous pressure point of heat and energy.
但太空叉这么有经验 肯定早就预料到这件事情啦~
But surely SpaceX with their years of experience could see this problem coming.
马一龙：本来不打算在博卡奇卡建导流槽 但后来发现自己还是图样
所以看来的确是因为没有导流槽才导致Starship测试出现问题
So it seems like the lack of any flame diversion did cause problems for Starship.
那为什么太空叉就是不想建这种如此重要的发射场设施呢？
So why did SpaceX decide to skip this seemingly crucial part of a launch pad?
现实的原因是Starship在博卡奇卡的这块场地还处于非常早期的设计阶段
Realistically, the Starship launch mounts in Boca Chica are still at a very early design phase
太空叉很可能想先一步一步来 看看情况
and SpaceX are likely trying to see how much they can get away with.
而且火星上不可能有现成的发射架或着陆场
After all, there will be no launch or landing pads on Mars,
所以Starship需要自己应付这些问题
so Starship will need to be able to deal with debris all by itself.
虽然当前的发射场地还在建设起步阶段
Despite the current launch pads being very basic in their design,
但Starship的发射架仍然是与我们平常见到的火箭发射台非常与众不同的
Starship's launch pad will always be extremely different
to the traditional launch pads we've seen in the past.
因为Starship设计可以进行在轨燃料加注
Since Starship is designed to do in-orbit refueling,
所以所有的燃料管路都要通到火箭底部
all of the fuel lines need to be located at the bottom of the rocket.
从而让Starship可以在太空进行交尾 并传输燃料
This will allow Starships to dock tail-to-tail in space and transfer propellants.
大多数火箭燃料管路会放在火箭的侧面
On most rockets, the fuel lines are placed on the side of the rocket.
这样火箭的管路设计会更简单一点
This allows the rocket to have a simpler design in terms of plumbing
但这需要火箭侧面有更大的设备来为火箭提供燃料和电力
but it requires a much larger structure at the side of the rocket to feed the vehicle with fuel and power.
对于猎鹰九号火箭来说 这个东西叫“strongback”
During a Falcon 9 launch, this structure also known as the "strongback",
它会在火箭离地后立即向后摆开
quickly pulls away from the rocket as soon as it leaves the launch pad.
从而让strongback和上面的组件快速远离火箭的尾焰
This allows the strongback and all of its components to move out of the way of the rocket's flame
并减少后续的发射架维护工序
and minimize the amount of refurbishment needed for the launch pad.
这也是太空叉目前另一个亟待解决的问题
This is yet another problem that SpaceX are looking to solve.
他们不但让Starship完全可复用
Not only are they trying to make Starship fully reusable,
还打算造一个完全可复用的发射台
they are also trying to design a fully reusable launch pad.
他们打算是让Starship着陆后能在一小时内重新回到发射架上准备发射
They want the launch pad to be so reusable,
that a Starship can land and be placed back onto the launch pad in less than an hour.
为了达成这个目标 发射台需要能完全抵抗住Starship发动机尾焰的冲击
In order to achieve this, the launch pad will need to be fully resistant to debris
and the force of Starship's engines.
但飞起的碎片并不是唯一的麻烦所在
But debris is not the only problem,
参考 av31170749
发射时产生的噪音也会对火箭和发射台本身造成破坏
the sound produced during a launch can be extremely damaging to the rocket and the launch pad.
当火箭发动机点火工作的时候 尾焰的热流速度会超过音速
When a rocket fires up its engines, the hot gasses exceed the speed of sound
并与周围空气碰撞
and collide with the surrounding air.
产生冲击波 裹挟大量能量冲击发射台
This creates shockwaves which blast the launch pad with massive amounts of energy
并弹反回火箭自身
which reflect back onto the rocket.
在航天飞机首飞STS-1任务中
During the launch of the first Space Shuttle flight STS-1,
发动机产生的噪音损坏了固体火箭助推器上的几块防热瓦
the sound energy produced by the engines was powerful enough
to damage some of the protective thermal tiles on the solid rocket boosters.
因此多数火箭发射台会使用噪声抑制系统来抵消那部分能量
This is exactly why launch pads typically use sound suppression systems to absorb most of that energy.
最常用的方法是在火箭底部喷大量的水
The most common method is to spray large amounts of water beneath the rocket.
声波会被空气中的水吸收 温度升高
As the sound waves meet the water, they are absorbed by bubbles of air which contract and heat up,
把声波的机械能变为热能
turning the sound energy into heat energy.
但也有其他办法能解决噪声问题
But there are other methods used to fix the sound problem.
在哈萨克斯坦 毛子的联盟号火箭发射场
In Kazakhstan, where the Russian Soyuz rockets launch,
最低气温能降至零下40度 水早就冻上了
the temperatures can be as low as -40 degrees - so a water deluge system would simply freeze.
所以毛子把火箭架在一个非常高的导流槽上
Instead, the Russians suspend the rocket over a much larger flame trench
极大减少可能反射回来伤及火箭本身的冲击波
where there is very little in the way that could bounce shock waves back onto the rocket.
那太空叉为什么没有为Starship选择这些噪声抑制方法呢？
So why hasn't SpaceX chosen one of these methods for their Starship launch pad?
为了回答这个问题 我们需要了解太空叉造出Starship的最终目标
To answer this, we have to look at SpaceX's overall goal with their Starship rocket.
他们希望Starship能往返月球和火星 且几乎不进行翻新就能复用
They want Starship to be able to land on the Moon and Mars and return with little to no refurbishment.
火星上没有现成的发射场或着陆场
There are no launch or landing pads on Mars.
所以火星上的着陆很可能也会遇到被尾焰吹起的碎石和残片
That means landing on Mars will likely throw up similar problems,
with rocks and debris being thrown back at the rocket.
那既然火箭是设计用来去火星的
So, since this rocket is designed specifically for Mars,
那就没必要现在图方便在地球上设计一个发射台了
it doesn't make sense for SpaceX to cut corners now by taking off from pristine launch pads.
相反 他们就是想要设计一款能应对火星和月球表面复杂环境的火箭
Instead, they need to design the rocket in such a way
that it can handle the rough environments of the Martian and Lunar surfaces.
对于着陆月球 他们的解决方案是想办法减少着陆时吹起的碎石
One way in which they plan to get around this issue for the Moon
is by reducing the amount of debris that's kicked up during a landing.
月球着陆版的Starship会在顶端安装更小版本的发动机
The Lunar version of Starship will have smaller engines at the top of the vehicle
会在着陆时点火减速
which will ignite to slow the vehicle down during a landing.
旁白念的“40米” YouTube自带字幕内容是“50 meters” 这里按原字幕内容翻译
这些发动机的位置离月球表面至少50米
These engines will be at least 50 meters above the Lunar surface,
从而最大程度减少吹起的碎石
minimizing the amount of debris that gets kicked up.
对于月球来说 这个解决方案很不错
For the Moon, this is a great solution.
但这放到火星就不行了
However, this solution would not work on Mars.
因为火星上的重力比月球大得多
Since the gravity on Mars is much stronger than on the Moon,
Starship需要使用自己推力更大的猛禽发动机去执行着陆
Starship will need to use it's more powerful raptor engines to land.
而猛禽发动机又太大 只能放在火箭尾部
Since these engines are so large, they will remain at the bottom of the vehicle.
太空叉就只能另想其他办法保护发动机舱
SpaceX will therefore have no choice but to find a way to protect the engine bay from debris.
在猎鹰九号上 所有梅林发动机都被安装在“octaweb”的环形网状结构内
On the Falcon 9, all of the Merlin engines are attached to a structure known as the "octaweb".
所有发动机的主要部件都藏在铝结构内
Here, the main engine components are shielded behind an aluminium structure
只有发动机喷口暴露在外
with only the engine bells sticking out.
这很可能是为了在再入时保护发动机
This is mostly to protect the engines during reentry,
因为再入时发动机首当其冲
since the rocket enters the atmosphere with its engines first.
而Starship是肚子朝前进入大气的
Starship reenters the atmosphere belly first
但它也很可能会设计一个类似结构来保护猛禽发动机
but it will likely adopt a similar design in order to protect the raptor engines
从而在起飞着陆时免受碎石影响
from debris upon launch and landing.
随着太空叉的测试工程的推进
As SpaceX's test program continues,
他们很可能会测试让火箭在崎岖地形起降
it's likely that they'll try taking off and landing from rougher terrains,
从而模拟真实的火星着陆
to simulate a real landing on Mars.
在那次静态点火的发动机损毁后
After the recent static fire damage,
太空叉必须着手为他们大水塔的发动机舱内线缆做好保护了
SpaceX has started to shield the wiring in the engine bay behind steel pipes.
这很可能是给Starship添加各种防护所需的各种研发的第一步
This is likely the first of many developments that go towards armoring Starship,
这样它才能应付各种恶劣情况 并最终着陆火星
so it can handle the worst case scenarios when it eventually lands on Mars.
随着太空叉研发他们的Starship 他们掌握的知识技能也在不断扩张
So as SpaceX continues to develop Starship and expand their knowledge,
就像我们普通人一样
many of us are looking to do the same.
2020年即将过去 该为我们在新的一年做好打算了 那么有没有一款……
2020 is almost over and it's time to start thinking of ways to improve ourselves for next year.
With Blinkist, you can expand your knowledge whilst making sure your time is wellspent.
This app does an amazing job of condensing all the information in a book
down to just 15 minutes for you to read or listen to!
Blinkist also has a new feature called 'shortcasts' which condenses your favorite podcasts down to the most interesting parts.
If you want to try this out for free, sign up using the link below to get 7 days of unlimited access to over 3,000 non-fiction books.
Blinkist covers almost every topic imaginable but I'd recommend reading Elon Musk's fascinating biography written by Ashlee Vance.
After your free trial, you'll also get 25% off the normal membership price.
This special offer is only available for the first 100 people who sign up using the link below so don't miss out!
This is a great way to support the channel, so you can continue to learn more about all things space.
If you'd like to support the channel evenmore, consider becoming a Patron
where you can give your input on each video and get exclusive access to our Discord server.
感谢观看 我们下期视频见
Thank you very much for watching and I'll see you in the next video.